Coming up on the platform talk
We started torturing up Zubeda on August 1st of
2002, but in order to justify the program
the two
torturers
They were lying about it from the very beginning and being paid a hundred and eight million dollars for the contract
The CIA actively seeks to hire people who have sociopathic tendencies
You can try as hard as you possibly can to keep sociopaths out of the CIA
The truth of the matter is that sociopaths end up running the CIA
All of the corporate media has been compromised and I think because of that most Americans
Really don't understand what's going on in the world. Those are the words of former CIA officer John Kiriaku
Coming up next on the platform talk
Welcome to this episode of the platform talk. I am your host and facilitator Greg Ford
My guest today spent 14 years of his life in various roles as an analyst
Case officer and chief of counter-terrorism in Pakistan for the Central Intelligence Agency
He is responsible for the capture of then suspected al-Qaeda operative
Abu Zubeda
He is also the author of two books
The first the reluctant spy and the second I will mention a bit later
He's been a consultant on movies regarding realism and accuracy in the portrayal of the CIA
But he is most famously or infamously depending on your perspective
Known as the man who blew the whistle on enhanced interrogation i.e. waterboarding or torture under the George W. Bush administration
The man I'm talking about is John Kiriaku
John welcome to the platform talk podcast and thankful agreeing to take the time to speak to me
How are you doing today? Thanks for having me Greg doing well. Thank you
So according to the late senator John McCain your revelations to the press
Were instrumental in the passage of the McCain-Feinstein amendment outlawing torture yet
You're the only person to date that's been prosecuted for the CIA's interrogation practices and you weren't even convicted
For participation, but simply for the revelation of those practices. That is
Some severe irony. Yeah before we get into those circumstances
Let's just give a brief kind of overview of your career in CIA talk about how you're recruited
The episodes where you were more proud of working for your country and then lead into what we're talking about now
You bet I came to Washington the week after I turned 18 to go to college at George Washington University
I got a bachelor's degree there in Middle Eastern studies
And I stayed for grad school and was just finishing a master's degree in
legislative affairs when I was
Approached by my grad school advisor who it turned out was under cover. He was a CIA officer under cover
As a professor looking for people who might be
Good fit his words in the CIA's culture. And so just before I graduated
I was recruited into the CIA. I went through the security process and
Then started working for the CIA full-time on January the 7th 1990 and
My first the first half of my career for seven and a half years
I was an analyst working on Iraq and the second half of my career
I was a counterterrorism
Operations officer working at first it's kind of quaint now, but at first against European communist
terrorism
Mostly in Athens and then against al Qaeda in the Middle East and Pakistan now you're Greek
Yes, and I think in one of the
Interviews that I saw you were one of the rare individuals if not the only person who spoke Greek and Arabic. Is that correct?
Yeah, it's funny, you know in an organization as big as the CIA
Yeah, I was the only person who spoke both Greek and Arabic and then that sort of sets you up for
An assignment that they wanted to put you on that's right
The one of the the chiefs in the counterterrorism center said that it was it was far easier and far cheaper for them to
Take a linguist and teach him operations than it was to take an operations officer and teach him how to speak Arabic and Greek
You know with that said, I know in doing some background research on you
I've seen some very intriguing stories that you've talked about in terms of weapons training
Talked about a story one time where you actually learned how to crash cars and break
Barricades you want to talk about any of that stuff? Sure
You know one of the many classes that they that they give you when you
When you start doing operations training, it's called crash and bang. It's
weapons training I took a long course called
advanced counterterrorism operations training
Bomb making and defusing
We went out to the Nevada desert to do advanced counterterrorist driving
All kinds of stuff. I mean, I remember when I first started my operational training
We were going to jump out of the back of a seat of a c12
And I remember saying this was pre 9 11. So I said to a colleague of mine
Now when in the world am I going to have to jump out of the back of the plane? I'm going to be making my recruitments
diplomatic cocktail parties
Right, right and then what four years later
I'm in a plane over Afghanistan and I'm thinking I can't believe I have to jump out of the back of this plane
As you went through this training, I know you talked about the issue of jumping out of the back of a plane
Did you have an affinity?
For any of this stuff that it surprised you how good you were
At picking up a lot of a lot of the tradecraft that they teach you at the at the agency
You know, it's funny. I've given thousands of interviews and you're the first person to ask me that and and that's a really
Good question
When I first joined the agency and I was you know sitting in my cubicle thinking the big thoughts and writing papers
That nobody would read my boss said to me
You know, you would be a really good operations officer and I was like what what are you talking about?
and he said
People like to be around you. You're you're fun and I said, well, thank you and I kind of just dismissed it
And then years later when I did decide to switch over to operations
One of my one of my instructors said the same thing. He said you are always going to be the good cop
And I said, yeah, I don't really have it in me to be the bad cop
It's just not my nature
And he said but it's the good cops who make the recruitment
And I found that to be very true, you know knock on wood
I'm blessed that that I have broad interests. I can talk about sports or opera or
Weapons or you know, whatever I can talk about it and people do like to be around me for the most part and so
If if the goal is to
Target someone for recruitment
I can do that
If if somebody just walks in off the street and volunteers to be recruited anybody can do that
But to actually develop a relationship with someone who doesn't realize that he's being recruited
Yeah, I I was good at that
Look, let's let's get into more of the serious stuff. I know you said, you know post 9 11
You were doing counterterrorism stuff
and
Then of course talked about the fact that a colleague
Approached you said hey, listen, would you like to be trained in enhanced interrogation?
Lead us through that
Right. So I was in pakistan as the as the chief of counterterrorism operations there
And we had caught up as a beta on the night of march 22nd and not just mark, but not just I was a beta
but
I'm not allowed to say the number still but it's many dozens of al-qaeda fighters and three or four senior al-qaeda leaders camp commanders
And so on I finished my tour in pakistan. I went back to headquarters and on the strength of that
I got promoted. I got a medal. I got a promotion. I got an amazing onward job
So I was in a cafeteria one day
And one of my colleagues who was a senior counterterrorism officer came up to me in the cafeteria and he said
Oh, hey, I'm glad I ran into you. I wanted to ask you and he said this very casually
Would you be interested in being trained in the use of enhanced interrogation techniques?
And I had never heard that term before
This was may of 2002
So I asked him what he meant and he said we're going to start get rough with these guys
And I said, well, what's that mean? And then he described these 10
techniques
And I said, I don't know man. That sounds like a torture program to me
And he said no, it's not torture. It's been approved by the white house and it's been approved by the justice department
I said, uh, let me think about it for an hour
So I went up to the seventh floor of the cia. That's the executive level. There was a very very senior cia officer
For whom I had worked a decade earlier in the middle east and I knocked on his door and I said, hey, I need some advice
And I told him what had happened
And his advice was very clear
He said first of all, let's call it what it is. It's a torture program
They can use whatever euphemism they want, but this is a torture program
Secondly, torture is a slippery slope and you know how these guys are somebody's going to go overboard
And they're going to kill a prisoner and then there's going to be a congressional investigation
And then there's going to be a justice department investigation and somebody's going to go to prison
Do you want to go to prison? And I said, no, I don't want to go to prison
As you mentioned in your intro, I was the only one who went to prison in the end
But I said, no, I don't want to go to prison
I went back downstairs to the counterterrorism center and I said, this is a torture program
I have a moral and ethical problem with it and I don't want anything to do with it and
As it turned out and this is one of the sources of great disappointment for me
They had asked 14 people if they wanted to be trained and I was the only one who said no
And the reason why they're so disappointing is because these guys were my friends
You know our our kids played together our wives
Were friends we would hang out with each other and barbecue and
I just I didn't realize until that day that they had it in their hearts to
You know to torture and in several cases to kill another human being in cold blood
But they did
So, uh, you know after that decision despite the fact that I had captured up as beta
In the next in the next
Round of promotions I was skipped over
And I was skipped over because as the head of counterterrorism said to my promotion panel
I had displayed a shocking lack of commitment to counterterrorism
Only because I I wouldn't agree to the torture training
Yeah, that's
That leads into some stuff. I want to ask you in a moment, but
You know, I wanted to challenge you a little bit one of the interviews that I saw with you
Says that you were not interested in participating or being trained
Yet you thought that it was necessary. Am I quoting you correctly?
I yeah, but I do missing a nuance
Okay. Yeah, so I was going to ask you to explain that on the surface explain the dichotomy of that statement. Yes
So we started torturing up as a beta on august 1st of 2002
Um, I said that I had an ethical and moral problem with it
Uh, but the the reporting we were getting back from the field was showing that it was
That it was working
So I told brian ross on abc news in 2007
And and this is what I think most people missed
I thought that there were two sides to this number one. It was wrong
But number two did it work
And the reporting we were getting back from the field was saying that it worked
That turned out to be a lie and we didn't know it was a lie
Until the inspector general released his report in 2009
What happened was the cia and the fbi
Had non-compatible
computer systems
so when the fbi was in charge of
Interrogating up as a beta
The interrogator ali sufan was sending back his reporting in fbi channels
Now the fbi is really really good at interrogations and they've been good at interrogations
Since the nuremberg trials in 1946
So ali is reporting back what abu zubeda is telling him and that information is not making it into cia channels
So then the cia demands that they take over on august 1st
They do take over they began torturing him and he goes completely silent
But in order to justify the program
the two
torturers to contract
Psychologists michael and jesson take ali sufan's information
And type it into the cia system
Saying we're doing the program and he's given us the kitchen sink. Here it is and I said to one of the guys
You know, maybe i'm wrong about this. I mean, I still think that it's morally bankrupt
But in terms of getting the information, maybe i'm just wrong
Well, it turned out that no i wasn't wrong
They were lying about it from the very beginning and not just lying
You know to the policymakers, they were lying internally at the cia and being paid
108 million dollars for the contract by the way
So that was one of the nuances that that I just did not successfully convey in that news interview in 2007
Understood understood
So let's let's go to your conviction
You were prosecuted
under the
The intelligence identities protection act
And right and so that's which is a very specific one. So at from initially there were there were a few different counts
But the government settled on that particular one. Why did they do that? Oh, yeah
So, uh, when I was arrested on the day of my arrest, this was the first week of january 2012
They charged me with five felonies three counts of espionage
One count of violating the intelligence identities protection act of 1982 and one count of making a false statement
um
I hadn't committed espionage
They knew I hadn't committed espionage
But on the day of my arrest they came to my lawyers and they said
take a plea
45 years
And he might live to meet his grandchildren
And we just dismissed it outright. I'm not going to take a plea and serve 45 years
They came back a couple of weeks later on a monday and they offered me 10 years
Take the plea to espionage and do 10 years and I said
Talking to abc news is not espionage having lunch with the new york times is not espionage
It is on the other hand illegal to classify a crime
You know, if if the cia is doing something illegal
It's actually illegal to classify it in order to keep the information from the public
So I said i'm not doing 10 minutes
So that was a monday on wednesday. They came back with eight years and on
Friday, they came back with five years and my lead attorney
I had 11 attorneys and this was an a-list dream team of white power defense attorneys
Most of whom were volunteers pro bono
so
My lead attorney played okay chair said to me
I have been an attorney in washington for 52 years and I have never seen them come down in time like this
And I said, what do you mean? He said usually they'll come and say
The offer is 10 years you turn it down and the next offer is 12 or 15 and the next offer is 18
But they're coming down 45 to 10 to 8 to 5
And I said, why are they doing that and he said because they have a shit case and they know it's shit
We're going to trial
so
We didn't hear from them again for
wow
eight months, I suppose
and then finally they said
um
That they would drop all the charges except the intelligence identities protection act
And I would do three years and I turned that down
And then they came back and said best in final offer
two and a half years. I do 23 months and
They gave me 24 hours to think about it. My wife and I
stayed up literally all night
Discussing what to do. I was only the second person ever charged under the intelligence identities protection act
And the author of that act a guy named
Morton Halperin
Was part of my defense team. He was he wrote the law and he said that I should never have been charged with a crime in the first place
and um
And I had an op-ed
Written by joe biden saying that the law was unconstitutional on its face and should never have been passed
So
We decided that I was going to turn it down
So I emailed the attorneys around six six a.m. And I said my wife and I were up all night
We've been talking all night and there was no case law because only one of the person had ever been charged and she was an actual spy
so um
I said i'm turning it down. I'm going to trial
And uh, one of the lawyers emailed me and said put on a pot of coffee. We're on our way over
So they got to my house around seven o'clock
And I explained to them why we decided to turn it down. I didn't do anything wrong
I didn't break the law that this was a public service
And that I had an affirmative defense
One of them said
If you were my brother, I would beg you to take this deal
He said you don't understand
This is not and I'll never forget his words. He said this is not about justice
This is about mitigating damage
Take the deal and then the other one said
This could be a blip in your life or it could be the defining event in your life. Make it the blip
And it was it was those two who convinced me. Geez. That's that's chilling. It was awful
Well, can I interrupt you for one second?
One of the please go ahead one of the things that they taught me and this is very important
It's something that I that I say in speeches all the time
um pro-publica
The uh, the investigative website did a study in november of 2012 in which they found that the federal government wins
98.2 percent of its cases
And they they do that using two strategies. One is called venue shopping and the other is called charge stacking
So venue shopping is where they seek to charge you in the federal district where you are most likely to be convicted
And the most likely to get the severest sentence
The second one charge stacking is when they do what they did to me
They'll charge you with a whole bunch of felonies
Knowing that you haven't committed those felonies
They wait until you go bankrupt and then they come back and they say we'll drop all the charges
But one if you take a plea
Well, look, I I had a 1.8 percent chance of winning
I was facing 45 years in prison and my attorneys told me that
realistically if I were to lose the case I was going to get 12 to 18 years
So I had five kids at home. Do you at that point it's a math
Yeah, do you do you roll the dice knowing that you have a 1.8 percent chance of winning?
Of course not and that's why they win all their cases
You know, one of the things that I've gotten out of my notes here is that uh, there was a term. I think it was on your
democracy now
interview from a few years back
Right before you went in
And I think your attorney said that it was a quote selective
And vindictive prosecution
Right, right
So and then you know and then also I think the first thing I did when I was researching you
I read your article or the or sorry the article about you in the new yorker
And I highlighted one of the quotes here. It says which matters more kiriaku's motives
and his reliability
Or the fact that however inelegantly he helped to reveal that a sitting president ordered international crimes
And I just find that to be very very interesting and it fits right into what you just described
Your attorney saying that look they they're the federal government is here to mitigate and to make a point with you
They they got me for confirming the last name
Of a former colleague to a journalist that name was never made public
at the same time
That my case was going on there was a disgruntled former cia officer
In Bethesda, mariland who had a blog
Yelling and screaming about the cia and how they had screwed him
And he revealed the names of seven covert operatives and he was never
Charged and they he just put him out there on the internet
He was never charged with a crime before I went to prison
General Petraeus who was the director of the cia at the time
Had given to his adulterous girlfriend
the names of
More than a dozen undercover cia operatives. He was bragging to show her I remember that
I remember that story. He was not charged with a crime
So that's why my attorney said this was selective and vindictive prosecution. That's exactly what it was
The reason those other people weren't charged is because they didn't blow the whistle on the torture program
You know you you hear about these things and you watch movies about them and you watch documentaries
But every time you hear stories like this all I can do to shake my head. It's exhausting truly
It really is it really is
Speaking of exhausting, let's take a quick break and then we'll come back
And I want to talk to you about domestic and foreign policy and then also independent media
So we'll be right back hold tight to the other side
And we are back with john kiriyaku
We were speaking with john about his background how he became famous slash infamous
certain circles
Earlier in the introduction I had mentioned that john had written two books
His second book actually came about
After serving his 23 month sentence the book is called doing time like a spy
How the cia taught me to survive in prison
Can you give us just a little bit about how you ended up writing this book?
How you were able to do it in prison? Yeah, it actually started
The day that I got to prison at my sentencing my
Attorneys asked the judge to send me to a minimum security work camp a minimum security camp
Has no
Bars on the windows. There's no lock on the door
You're free to come and go as you please
You're just on your honor not to abscond and most of those guys work in town at the local university
So the prosecution had no objection
So she ordered that I be sent to a minimum security camp now camps normally are
Uh across the street from real honest to god prisons because if there's a riot or a lockdown
It's the guys in the camp who then go to the prison to do the cooking and the laundry and the you know
Mopping and stuff like that
So, um, I was I was told to turn myself in on february
When was it february 28th
2013 at the federal correctional institution at loretto pennsylvania
So, you know, it's funny. You just drive up there and you knock on the door and you say i'm here to turn myself in
So, uh, I did I went to the camp and they said go across the street to the prison
First they'll process you and then they'll walk you over here. I said, okay
so I go over to the prison I turn myself in
And um, they put me through the x-ray and then they you know pat me down
And then the the guard starts to lead me outside and around
To the back of the prison and I said no no
I'm supposed to be at the camp across the street
And he he chuckles and says not according to my paperwork. You're not
And I was like, oh my god
And then I thought take it easy. There's nothing you can do
I figured if I made a ruckus, I'll just end up in solitary. So I didn't say a word. I just went with it
So it took me it took me about 40 minutes to process me and
Then they took me to a cell and uh and just
Walked away
And I thought to myself you've been trained for this. You've lived in far worse places than this
You know how to handle it
So I decided that very first day that I would just use
The skills that the CIA gave me in training
To keep myself safe and to keep myself at the very top of the social heap
And that that became the book
wow
you give us one or two examples
of
Training that you were able to use in order to survive and and mitigate your circumstances in prison
What I do is is I have these 20 what I call life lessons that the CIA taught me
And I I list them in the very beginning of the book one of them for example is
Admit nothing deny everything make counter accusations
One of the things that I learned early on very early on when I first arrived there
Was that my my biggest enemies my biggest threats were going to be the guards
Not other prisoners and so you know repeatedly they tried to bait me into
Harming another prisoner they tried to bait me into
Getting into a fight so they could put me in solitary and I would never I'd never bite
So one one day I was called down into the lieutenant's office because there had been a fight in the uh
In the housing unit. It was quite a quite a serious fight like nearly a riot and um
And so everybody went into lockdown well the fight broke out in the tv room
And I just happened to be sitting right there six feet away from the two guys who started duking it out
And it ended up, you know involving a dozen guys and blood on the floor and stuff like that
But when there's a fight
What you do to protect yourself is just get up and get out as quickly as you can
So they called me down said, uh, what about this fight?
And I thought to myself admit nothing deny everything make counter organizations. I said what fight
Oh, very funny. You didn't know there was a fight. I said, I don't know anything about any fight
Yeah, well, we have witnesses that say you were right there when it started and I said, yeah
I think maybe you were there when it started. Maybe you're the one who started it
What the do I know about any fight? I think you're the only ones who pick fights around here
And you know, we went back and forth like this for several minutes and finally they became so frustrated. They told me get out of here
So in the end they got nothing from me
And uh, I came out ahead. They were trying to implicate me in the fight and then you know, there are other ones like
And then folks know that you're not a snitch and people know i'm not a snitch
Exactly, which is why I was adopted by the italians because I hate the fbi as much as they do
And I was not a rat and you know, there are other things like let others do your dirty work
Another one is you're stronger than you realize you are
Stuff like that. So when these situations present themselves and you need to worry about yourself and your own safety and your own protection
It just kicks in and it's actually it was actually comforting, you know, much to my surprise too
Let me back up. I had to write this book in in long hand
because
You don't have access to typewriters or computers or anything like that and the cops just to be told to me
Whenever they would shake me down and they would go through my locker
They would find the draft of the book and they would destroy it
They would tear it up and throw it at me
And so what I ended up doing was every time I would finish a chapter
Uh, I would have it smuggled out
By another prisoner and sent to my attorney
And my attorney held the draft for me. So I ended up having to write the book twice in long hand
and um
When I got out, uh, I I put it all in the computer
I did several rounds of editing and I ended up winning one of the country's big four
Uh literary awards. I won the pen first amendment award
Which along with the pen Faulkner
The Pulitzer and the Edgar Allen Poe are the the four big literary awards
And then it was named memoir of the year by forward reviews
So it ended up doing pretty well
Congratulations. I didn't know. Thank you. Yeah
Let's transition into, um, some domestic and formal policy
But before we go there because I want to play something for you
And then I want to read some commentary. So let me play this for you really quickly
This is something I'd heard about a while ago and then finally pulled it up
This is a statement made by former CIA director and former secretary of state Mike Pompeo
I was the CIA director. We lied. We cheated. We steal stole
It's like we we had we had entire we had entire training courses
It uh
It reminds you of the uh, uh the glory of the American experiment
So that's a statement. I'm sure you've heard about that statement. And then I also
I was watching a TED talk you did
at Foggy Bottom
And you know, I'm just leaping through some of the comments and one comment caught my eye
And it said
The CIA is filled with psychopaths
And I bring these I bring these two examples up because how do you
foresee or how concerned are you
About this current ideological polarization
That is affecting the country at large and how you perceive that impacting
people in the intelligence community and their ability
to
Yeah, objectively evaluate information in the national interest without having without having to be colored
By their own particular biases
That's a great question. Um, I'm very worried about the direction of the country
I mean, you know, we read these articles about Q and on and
And and the notion that the democrats stole the election. I think I think all of that is silliness. It's all nonsense. What's dangerous though
is that
when people believe
Rumors when they're
Exorded by a president to to
For example, take back their government and and storm the capital
Um that people believe him literally
And the reason why I'm so worried about it is not even necessarily that people are angry and willing to take to the streets
We took to the streets in, you know, 1917. We took to the streets in 1968
These things happen sometimes. That's cyclical. What's scary though
is
What the proposed response is
My former boss in both pakistan and headquarters robert grenier
Wrote an article for wrote an op-ed for the new york times several weeks ago in which he advocated using cia
counter insurgency techniques
against
Right-wing protesters
Okay, I consider myself to be
solidly
left-wing
But what he advocated was essentially murdering people
Whose politics you disagree with
Well, if we're supposed to be a nation of laws, we're supposed to be
A beacon of human rights and hope and democracy
You can't just advocate
the wholesale
slaughter of people when you don't like their politics
And you don't like that they took to the streets to exercise their constitutional rights
So that's what I think is is the most dangerous
Point where
Politics and the cia come together and I want to add one other thing that I think is important and I'd like your listeners to know
I was very friendly with a cia psychiatrist
Even after I left the cia and he retired. We've remained friends
We did a couple of operations together. Well while I was inside
You know in the cia
So he told me one time very casually
That the cia actively seeks to hire people who have sociopathic tendencies
He was specific to say that they don't like to hire sociopaths
Because sociopaths have no conscience. They're unable to feel remorse or regret
And they blow right through a polygraph exam because they they can't feel guilt
But if they can't feel guilt they can't be controlled
People who have sociopathic tendencies
Do feel guilt they do have a conscience
But they're happy to break the law or to work in moral or legal gray areas
I was happy to break the law because I believed in my heart that we were the good guys
Right, so if my country is attacked like it was on september 11th
I want to go over there and fight and
Capture people and you know make sure it never happens again
The problem is that just by their very nature sociopaths slip through the process and like in corporate america
They rise to the top to leadership positions
at the cia and so
You can try as hard as you as you
Possibly can to keep sociopaths out of the cia the truth of the matter is that sociopaths end up running the cia
and that's why you have
you have things like
secret prisons assassination programs
Torture programs
Domestic spying
It's because they can't help themselves
And that's why we need robust oversight which we haven't had since the 1980s
I'm glad you you you provided that insight and I want to you know get your analysis on you know
We've got a new administration
Coming after of course the trump administration
In many of my private conversations with my friends
Some of my personal posts on facebook. I get into I get dragged quote unquote as they say because I say
I like you i'm solidly left. I don't consider myself a democrat. I consider myself a progressive
But the thing is is that I consistently say that the democrats are not the good guys
I just call them a less openly rapacious
version of political governance
and so
In the biden administration coming, I'm not expecting much
But in terms of what you have outlined in terms of the uh the goals and initiatives of the cia
You've got the situation with venezuela. You have a biden administration that is still
working to
install wanguaido somebody who is
not a
democratically elected leader you have situations now where
Where biden's administration is still seeking to extract concessions
from iran
For doing nothing more than abiding by the treaty that the united states broke
That happened and you've got the syrian airstrike
Where we're continuing
us imperialism all the while
Still looking
You know shining the light on trump like hey trump is this bad guy
But here we are enacting some of the same policies. I remember when trump
Had his missile attack. No, he did not seek congressional approval
And msnbc and cnn and most neoliberals had a field day with that yet not nary a peep
Now that biden has done it and so what are your thoughts on
Especially having the the vast experience that you do behind the scenes and also being able to comment on
You know the fact that you are actually in media now
What is your thought process on us foreign policy? What should people expect?
What can people
Maybe hope to affect through through public and political activism. What are your thoughts on that?
And you just said it
There is practically no difference between the biden foreign policy and the trump foreign policy
Just like there was practically no difference between the obama foreign policy and the george w bush foreign policy
Look, there's only there are only three ways in which you can do anything
militarily in another country
Three ways number one if you are invited by that country to go in number two if that country attacks you
And number three with the express
Voted approval of the united nations security council
So if you bomb another country like we bombed syria last week or like
Donald trump bombed syria four years earlier. That is a war crime
period
It's not open to negotiation. It's a war crime. There was no congressional authority to do it
and like you say
nary a peep
The only democrat who said anything
Was was tim kane a democrat from virginia
And he didn't say anything four years ago when it was donald trump bombing syria
So I I agreed
right
And representative rocona has spoken of the sets of things as well
And and a handful of other progressives, but for the most part people are silent
But look at libya. We have wrecked that country and for what the libyans didn't do anything to us
Because we didn't like their politics
You can't just bomb countries every time you decide you don't like their politics
And then it also opens up this
this
You know two-faced policy that we have where where you've got for example, saudi arabia
Where where they actually carry out crucifixions
Uh over the course of the year right they crucified a 16 year old last year
I was not aware of that. So we've we've got this two-faced foreign policy. Right. That's just
indefensible
I i'm exactly like you are I consider myself to be from the political left
I am absolutely not a democrat because I don't think the democrats are trustworthy
right
Let me ask you one more section of this before we take a second break
In regards to the the attack on syria, you know
I don't want to I don't want to go tinfoil hat here
but I have
heard speculation for many years now that the cia
Has infiltrated corporate media
And I I bring that up only to get your analysis on the fact that
What is problematic to me and this leads into our next section on independent media is that
No one I have seen
Certainly not cnn certainly not the new york time not that not the post not msnbc has talked about the fact that
framed response
That the syrian airstrike is about neglects to provide the context
That the individuals who who we quote unquote retaliated against
Are simply individuals who have attacked us installations in a country
That we have been expressly asked to leave
Yes, that's that's really the the bottom line here
We attacked last week iraqi nationals
Right because they attacked us troops who occupy their country
I mean it's it's it really would be laughable if it wasn't so serious
But yeah, that's that's really the bottom line. That's really the bottom line
It's it's awful. What has happened to our foreign policy and
When I say awful, I mean it's awful because nobody questions it
Let me answer your question about the cia infiltration of the corporate media
It's not as uh
late as it was under operation mockingbird
Before 1975 before the church committee put an end to it
The cia actively recruited members of the media including the american media
That doesn't happen anymore not just because it's illegal
But more importantly because it doesn't need to happen. They don't need to recruit people. What they do
Is they take these national security correspondence
And I'll use ken dilanian of nbc and msnbc as an example. So what they do is
They'll they'll call him and say hey, we've got a little scoop for you and they'll leak some classified information
and he'll print a
A very interesting story. He used to be with the la times and then he was with the new york times and now msnbc and nbc
So he'll say oh exclusive report
Intelligence sources say what wasn't intelligent sources that said it
It was the cia's office of public affairs the press officer leaked the story to you to make you happy
There there's a fantastic
Journalist at buzzfeed by the name of jason leopold
uh the pentagon
during the obama administration
Referred to jason leopold in a memo as a foyer terrorist a freedom of information act terrorist
Because he's filed more freedom of information act request than any other journalist
He's the one who broke the hillary clinton email story, for example, and he got all that from foyer
So he's out there actually doing his job. He'll file a foyer request and when
When the agency or department doesn't respond within the requisite 90 days
He files a lawsuit and he invariably wins and that's how he gets the stories
well
In the course of his foyer request with the cia he asked for
all communications
Between the cia's office of public affairs and journalists
And they had to send him thousands and thousands of pages of stuff. Well, these included
An email from kandelinian
To the cia where he had written an article and he had sent it to the cia
Before he sent it to his own editor
For cia approval
Now, why would he do something like that?
Because he's in the cia's pocket like every other national security journalist in washington
And the cia has told him look you write nice things about us and we'll leak
Important and interesting information to you
But if you don't write nice things about us you are cut off
And you will never interview a cia person ever again
So they don't have to recruit journalists. They just threaten them
Absolutely incredible
Well, john, look, let's take our final break and we'll come back and we'll discuss the need for and the perception of independent media
And try to squeeze a little bit of domestic policy in there
Once again, this is john kiriyaku
And this is the platform talk. We'll be right back after this final break
When the president talks to god, I wonder which one plays the better cop
We should find some jobs to get us broke. No, they're lazy, george. I say we don't just give them more liquor stores and dirty coke
That's what god recommends
When the president talks to god, do they drink near beer and go play golf?
While they pick which countries to invade which muslim souls still can be saved
I guess god just calls a spade a spade when the president talks to god
When the president talks to god, does he ever think that maybe he's not that that voice is just inside his head
When he kneels next to the presidential bed, does he ever smell his own bullshit when the president talks to god?
If you're enjoying the platform talk podcast, you should visit the platform website
The platform website is a place where news issues and current events are aggregated into categories such as social justice
politics international affairs
history race and culture
Just to name a few so just visit
www.theplatform.fyi and
Why not just go one step further and lend your support through patreon
Patreon is basically an online tip jar for a job well done
And if a job well done is what you think is happening
Please consider becoming a patron and you can support this project weekly monthly or make a one-time donation for whatever amount
You think is appropriate and or sustainable. You can do that by visiting patreon. That's pat reon
dot com
forward slash platform productions and click on the become a patron button
Look forward to your support and thanks again for listening
And we are back for our final segment with john kiriyaku
Last segment we talked about foreign policy
john has made some very very
stunning
revelations
I'm sure he's used to that. So right now we're going to go ahead and talk about independent media
And this actually is the main reason I ended up wanting to speak to to you john
I
Or you came across my radar probably the spring of last year
I listened to
A number of different independent media sources. I start my day with democracy now in the morning
And wpf w in dc
And then I later on the afternoon when I can I listened to by any means necessary
And then I used to listen to your show that you did with brian becker called loud and clear
Two shows that I've really really
Thoroughly enjoyed and I was uh very very sad and um, I just turned it on one day and you guys were gone
And then I found you again quote unquote
listening to
That same time slot
You have now partnered with lee stranny hand formally of breitbart
That's an interesting pairing
For me
But um, you know, nonetheless, so I want to talk to you quickly about how you got involved with radio sputnik
Your partnership with brian becker and then how you
Ended up with uh, sure any hand and then I'll get some other stuff go ahead prison for about a year
And um, I was sort of you know, like any convicted felon with a degree or without a degree or multiple degrees in my case
um, I couldn't find a job and the only job I had was uh,
Was uh working for a progressive think tank called the institute for policy studies the oldest left-wing think tank in washington
But I was making minimum wage and I had to raise my own salary
Doing go fund me campaigns, which believe me is is hard
so, uh
Sputnik approached me and they said hey, would you be interested in your own radio show and all my life?
I've wanted to do radio, but I turned them down
I thought no, I just can't work for the russians
Right people are going to accuse me of being a spy and a sellout and all this stuff
So I turned them down and I continued looking for a job couldn't find one finally
I went back to them
And I said you still have an opening for a radio show and they said yeah, we have this show with brian becker
Um, we're gonna spend some money on advertising. Uh, if you'd like to pair up with him we can do that
And so I didn't know brian other than
I had been on a show one time and so I paired up with brian. It was a natural fit
I have such deep respect and admiration for brian becker
I learned so much from the guy. He's
Far to the left of me. I mean, I consider myself sort of a
A mainstream
Progressive, um, but he's he's a marxist and he's very
Clear about his his ideology which was fun for me because he taught me a lot and he opened up
He opened up a world that I would never have had access to
Um in in that he's friendly with all of these vietnam era
Uh progressives and not just progressives, but black panthers and weather underground and you know people that I've read about in the history books
That he's introduced me to so we really hit it off in that show and it was a very newsy show
But what I did when they first offered me the job
was I said
I said I I I do have a demand
Um, I said I want to be able to talk about any issue that I want
And about any person that I want
And I want to be able to criticize
Even if it's latin mere putin and they said done
And I said put it in writing in the contract
Done and they did they put it in writing and I can tell you that never one single time
Has anybody at sputnik ever asked me to say something or to not say something about any issue?
And so I've had like utter freedom to talk about anything. I want to talk about at sputnik
So I ended up getting offered
In the summer of 2020 a corporate job and this was going to be my big comeback
They offered me more money than I have ever fantasized about making
So I I
I gave sputnik three weeks notice. I said I have this job. I just can't possibly turn it down
and um
And so I left effective september the first
As it so happened
Our contracts all ran out on september the first or on august the 31st
and um
It was coincidental that as I was leaving
Brian and our two producers walters molarec
and nicole roussell
Kind of had a something of a contract dispute with
Sputnik and then they just decided to go their own way and to produce their own
podcast so the show just ended
Well, I I take this corporate job. I'm really excited
And I'm starting to see things
and I'm thinking
This is money laundering
So I called a friend of mine who spent 30 years with the fbi and I said
I'm not an expert on these issues
But here's what I'm seeing and I'm thinking it's money laundering
And she said, oh, yeah, this is money laundering
That explains why that's more money than I've ever dreamed of
So I ported it to the fbi
And I called sputnik and I said, hey, I've had a change in plans if you'll have me back
I'd love to come back and they said perfect. We're going to pair you with lea strannahan
And that's how it happened
Okay, what that's that's certainly wasn't what I was expecting to hear that's
Let me make a quick point. I'm sure you heard of or heard about
Joe by this press secretary Jen sake
She made a sort of a snarky statement about rt
Which is russian television and and sputnik right as being
Instruments of propaganda
I want to quickly what you know, what were your what was your initial response to that?
I knew her when she was working for john carry just after I left carry staff and she goes to my church
So she's a big she's a big star now in the greek-american community. Um
Yeah, Jen Jen sake is just plain wrong
She's just wrong. Yes rt and sputnik are are owned by the russian government
But my own experience is one where I have an unfettered ability to
Say anything that I want to say
It's it's on it's on us corporate media and mainstream media that I'm censored
You know, that's the only place I have
I have trouble conveying my
Positions on issues not with sputnik
It's interesting that you say that because the other sputnik show that I listen to regularly is
The critical hour with dr. Wilma leon
And yes, he is and and he's also added garland nixon who used to be on with lee strannahan in the morning show
But you know, it's very interesting. Uh at one point dr. Leon was making a statement about
He was either invited to speak on cnn or msnbc
And they were trying to sort of vet his position
On whatever topic they were inviting him on to speak about and I've never forgotten this
I thought it was so amusing but so profound at the same time
He said i'm a political scientist not a political operative
And I thought that was so very
Telling and and amusing and also chilling at the same time that you would even need to say something like that
Fox a lot as crazy as that sounds I
I was on the tecker carlson show nine times last year
Uh, but I didn't make a single appearance on msnbc. I was on cnn once
Tucker carlson calls me like renowned cia whistleblower john kiriyaku
cnn calls me cia torture whistleblower john kiriyaku msnbc
Every time they refer to me. They call me cia leaker john kiriyaku
Yeah, the washington post and I've written for the washington post
But apparently the left hand doesn't know what the right hand's doing over there
But the washington post did an article last year where they listened to
Butnic radio shows for a week and then they wrote about sputnik
So they they happened to listen to our show
On a thursday and thursday is the day that we had this regular weekly segment called criminal injustice
Where we had uh kevin gestala who's a journalist with shadowproof right and paul right who's the publisher of prison legal news
And criminal legal news magazines and the head of a think tank called the human rights defense center
So, uh, you know every week we would spend a half an hour and talk about
The latest cases the latest legislation relative to criminal justice and and prison reform and things like that
So the washington post listened to this 30 minute segment and they said that we
weakened democracy
Those were the words that they used we weakened democracy
By criticizing the justice system
So that's clearly russian propaganda, right?
Because because we shouldn't be saying that it's inhumane for example for uh
For angola prison in louisiana to hold a man in solitary confinement for 44 years
That's not what weakens the country what weakens the country is john kiriyaku talking about it
ridiculous
correct
It it's it's amazing and you know, it's you know, that leads me to my next point slash question for you
Would you say the us electorate is compromised by corporate media?
And the other question is and you can tackle these in whatever order you want
On a scale of one to ten. How uninformed is the us electorate?
uninformed first of all the the answer to your first question is yes people are compromised and don't forget that that
What the conservatives say notwithstanding
Fox is also part of the corporate media structure. So it's all of them. It's fox. It's msnbc. It's cnn
It's it's all of them and even democracy now as much as I love democracy now
They've taken a decided turn to the to the right on foreign policy
And I find them to be very neoliberal on most of these foreign policy issues. So, um
Yeah, I think that all of the the media
All of the corporate media has been uh compromised and I think because of that
Most americans really don't understand what's going on in the world
Also, you know, we're very parochial in our views. We always have been parochial. That's why we had for example
The know-nothing party. That's why we fought kicking and screaming going into the the first world war
Uh, it was it was because people
Are uninformed about foreign policy. They don't uh, they don't want to get involved in overseas entanglements
Which believe me is not a bad thing
But that translates into being uninformed, you know, how many of your friends read Al Jazeera?
Let's say or I'll monitor or even bbc, which in and of itself is government run propaganda
When I wake up in the morning, I read the post the times the journal the la times
cnn msmbc fox and then I go to the alternative media every day
consortium news reader supported news
zero hedge spotnik
Al Jazeera, I'll monitor
I look at some of the smaller middle east papers because I live there
I read the greek press every morning because they give you an example or an idea rather of what's going on
The eastern Mediterranean you've got to read everything
And then make up your own mind
And you really need to have all sides of a story in order to make your own informed
A position. It's the only way to do it
Right, right. So john, you know, I know I've kept you far longer than I promised your wealth of information
Let's say you and I were sitting with somebody who
is content
To trust cnn and msmbc
And most of what we call mainstream news. What would you say to them to try to coax them
Into opening their minds
To go outside of what they consider to be the norm and the reason why I ask this question is that I have a regular weekly call with
A very good friend
We do a bible study with his father in the afternoons and I had mentioned the intercept to him
And his first response to me was well greg, you know
Now first of all, he'd never heard of the intercept and then his first response to me was well, greg
You know, we just have to be careful about fake news
Now that wasn't the time or the place to really challenge him on that
But my thought process was, you know, it's very interesting is that this gentleman has known me for a while
and
I think he has a fairly high opinion of me, but yet and still
the first thing
That he thought to respond with
For a a news source that he had never heard of
Was to presume that it might be fake news simply because it wasn't in nrms nbc
What would you say to someone like that to at least sort of soften
Softened them up for wow stepping outside of what they consider to be mainstream. I would have to reiterate
what I what I just said that
We need as much information as we can possibly take in so that we can draw our own conclusions
We can't rely on any one or two outlets to decide for us
What issues we should be informed on and so there's nothing wrong with doing your own research
If you think something might be fake
By all means research it but take in as much information as you possibly can
Well, John, I think we can leave it there. I want to thank you so much for your time man
This has been so enlightening for me. Let us know how we can keep up with show a backstory
And then if anybody wants to follow you on twitter or instagram or any social media
I'm at
www.johnkiriaku.com
And you can hear the backstory every day monday through friday on sputnik radio
I think it's after 7 p.m. They turn it into a podcast and it's on all the usual platforms
Okay
Again, my guest has been jar kiriako. This is Greg for the platform talk. Thank you for listening beautiful and we will talk to you next time
You've just listened to another episode of the platform talk podcast
Our guest today was former cia analyst case officer and counterterrorism operative
John kiriaku
The musical selection in our first break was bodies
By drowning pool
A song often used in enhanced interrogation by the cia
The musical selection in our second break was when the president talks to god by bright
The opening theme for the platform talk podcast is social insecurity by odyssey
And the closing theme for the platform talk podcast is no rules for kings
Also by odyssey
I want to thank you again for taking the time to listen and as usual stay enlightened and stay informed